So where are you?
我在哪里？
You're in some motel room.
某间旅馆房内
You just... You just wake up, and you're in a motel room.
一觉醒来，发觉自己在旅馆房内
There's the key.
钥匙在这里
It feels like maybe it's the first time you've been there, but...
似乎刚刚住进来，但…
perhaps you've been there for a week, three months.
又似乎住了一个星期甚至三个月
It's kind of hard to say. I don't... I don't know.
很难说，我…我不知道
It's just an anonymous room.
只是间普通的房间
This guy.
这个人…
He's here already.
已经来了
Lenny!
莱尼！
It's Leonard...
是莱纳
like I told you before.
我告诉过你
Did you? I must have forgot.
是吗？我一定是忘了
I guess I've already told you about my condition.
我大概提到过我的病
Oh, well, only every time I see you.
每次见面都提
My car.
我的车
This is your car.
这是你的车
Oh, you're in a playful mood.
玩我
It's not good for you to make fun of someone's handicap.
你不应该捉弄有缺陷的人
Just trying to have a little fun.
只是开开玩笑
Roll up your window.
绞起玻璃窗
It's broken.
是破的
I can get that fixed for you.
我可以修理
So where to, Sherlock?
你想去哪？福尔摩斯先生？
I got a lead on a place.
我要去一个地方
Oh, what the hell do you wanna go there for?
你跑那里到底想搞什么名堂
You know it?
你认识这地方
Yeah, it's just this fucked-up building. Why do you wanna go there?
只是间破屋子，为什么去？
Don't remember.
想不起来了
Looks like somebody's home.
似乎有人
Ah, that thing's been here for years.
车已经停了好几年了
What are you talking about? These tracks are only a few days old.
路上的痕迹是新的
Tracks? What are you? Pocahontas?
你懂得认痕迹？
Come on!
来吧
Let's take a look inside.
进去看看
"Teddy."
泰迪
"Don't believe his lies. He is the one. Kill him."
不要受他骗，是他，杀了他
I finally found him.
我终于找到他了
How long have I been looking?
我找了多久？
Find anything?
找到什么吗？
Didn't think so.
大概没有
Let's go, huh?
我们走吧
Oh, fuck this.
算了
You're gonna pay for what you did.
杀人偿命
Beg forgiveness, and then you pay.
一命还一命！
You don't have a clue, you freak.
神经病，你搞错了！
Beg my wife's forgiveness before I blow your brains out.
先向我太太认错，然后受死
Leonard, you don't know what's going on.
莱纳，你真是糊里糊涂的
-You don't even know my name. -Teddy.
-知道我叫什么吗？ -泰迪
That's 'cause you read it off a fucking picture.
你靠照片才知道
You don't know who you are.
你不知道自已是谁
I'm Leonard Shelby. I'm from San Francisco.
我叫莱纳・谢尔比，旧金山人
That's who you were.
那是以前的你
That's not...
不是…
what you've become.
现在的你
-Shut your mouth. -You want to know, Lenny?
-住口 -你想知道吗？
Come on. Come on, let's go down to the basement.
来，我们到地下室去
Let's go down, you and me, together.
一起下去
Then you'll know who you really are.
你会知道自己真正是谁
It's just an anonymous room.
只是间普通的房子
There's nothing in the drawers. But you look anyway.
抽屉空空如也，只管打开看看
Nothing except the Gideon Bible,
只有本基甸社送的圣经
which I, of course, read religiously.
我当然诚心阅读了
You know, you know who you are,
你知道自己是谁
and you know kind of all about yourself.
对自己身份有点印像
But just for day-to-day stuff,
至于过日常生活…
notes are really useful.
字条十分有用
Sammy Jankis had the same problem, but he really had no system.
杰克斯・萨米也靠字条，不过他缺乏条理
He wrote himself a ridiculous amount of notes, but he'd get them all mixed up.
他拼命写字条，却乱放一通
You really do need a system if...
要有效果…
if you're gonna make it work.
就要有条理
I'm Mr. Shelby from 304.
我是304号房的住客
What can I do for you, Leonard?
有什么可以效劳？莱纳
Burt.
我叫波特
Burt. I'm not sure. I think I may have asked you to hold my calls.
我可能说过，我不接电话
You don't know?
你记不得？
I'm not too good on the phone.
我不习惯讲电话
Right. You said you like to look people in the eye when you talk to them.
对，你喜欢面谈
You don't remember saying that?
你不记得说过？
Well, that's the thing. I have this condition.
我有种病
Condition?
病？
It's my memory.
我的记忆
Amnesia?
失忆？
No, no, no. It's different from that. I have no short-term memory.
不是，我没有短期记忆
I know who I am. I know all about myself.
我知道自己是谁，不过…
Since my injury, I can't make new memories.
自从受了伤，我没有新记忆
Everything fades.
什么都记不住
If we talk for too long, I'll forget how we started.
我会忘记为什么跟你谈
The next time I see you, I'm not gonna remember this conversation.
我会忘记跟你谈过
I don't even know if I've met you before.
我甚至记不得见过你
So if I seem a little strange or rude or something, uh...
假如我行动古怪、无礼…
I've told you this before, haven't I?
我都说过，是不是？
Yeah. I mean, I don't mean to mess with you, but it's so weird.
是，确实太奇怪了
-You don't remember me at all? -No.
-你完全记不得我？ -记不得
-We've talked a bunch of times. -I'm sure we have.
-可是我们经常交谈 -可以肯定
Well, what's the last thing you remember?
你最后记得的是什么？
My wife.
我太太
What's it like?
是怎样的？
It's like waking. It's like you just woke up.
像是醒过来，像刚刚醒来
That must suck.
一定很不爽
It's all backwards, I mean.
全部都调转来
Like, maybe you get an idea about what you want to do next,
你或许知道要做什么
but you don't remember what you just did.
可是记不得做过什么
I'm exactly the opposite...
我却刚刚相反
-How long have I been staying here? -A couple of days.
-我在这里住了多久？ -几天
-And you're holding my calls? -Like you said.
-而你替我阻挡来电？ -就像你吩咐的
Okay, but this guy's an exception.
除了这个人
Do you know this guy?
认识他吗？
Yeah, it's your friend, right?
是你的朋友
What makes you think he's my friend?
你怎么知道？
I just saw you together, that's all.
我见过你们在一起
He's not my friend.
他不是我的朋友
If he calls or if he shows up here,
假如他打电话来…
you give me a call in my room, okay?
或者亲自来，通知我
-What, his name's Teddy? -Teddy, yeah.
-他叫泰迪？ -泰迪，对了
All right.
好的
Look, I hope my condition's not gonna be a problem for you.
我希望没有给你添麻烦
No, not as long as you remember to pay the bill.
只要你记得结账就行
-Forty. -Forty.
-4O块 -4O块
This guy...
那个人…
He's here already.
已经来了
Lenny!
莱尼！
You really need a system if you're gonna make it work.
要有效，就要有条理
You kind of learn to trust your own handwriting.
要相信自己的笔迹
That becomes an important part of your life.
那是日常生活的重要部分
You write yourself notes.
你为自己写备忘字条
And where you put your notes... That also becomes important.
放字条的地方，也很重要
You need a jacket that's got like six pockets in it.
外衣要有六个口袋
Particular pockets for particular things.
各个口袋有各自的功能
You just kind of learn to know where things go and how the system works.
要养成井井有条的习惯
You have to be wary of other people writing stuff for you,
要防范别人故意混淆你
that it's gonna lead you astray.
替你乱写字条
I mean, I don't know how these people try and take advantage of somebody
世上总有那种人
with this condition. If you have a piece of information...
把关键的资料纹在身上…
which is vital, writing on your body instead of on a piece of paper can be the answer.
是行得通的办法
It's just a permanent way of keeping a note.
可以永久备忘
Who is this?
谁？
"Remember Sammy Jankis."
记住杰克斯・萨米
-Excuse me, sir. You left these at your table. -Thanks.
-对不起，你忘记拿走 -谢谢
Uh... Lincoln Street?
林肯街怎么去？
Oh, yeah, just go straight out on Sixth Street.
沿第六街一直向东走
I'm gonna write this down.
等一等，我要写下来
It's easy. Just go...
很容易，只是直走
Trust me. I need to write this down.
我的确需要写下来
Discount Inn.
特惠旅馆
Natalie.
娜塔莉娅
My car.
我的车
Teddy.
泰迪
'John Edward Gammell."
约翰・爱德华・盖玛
This guy told me his name was Teddy.
他自称泰迪
"Don't believe his lies."
不要受他骗
-Mr. Gammell? -Lenny, is that you?
-盖玛先生？ -是你吗？莱尼
John Gammell?
你是约翰・盖玛？
Lenny, it's Teddy. Stay there. I'll be right over.
是泰迪啊，不要走开，我立即来
Okay. I'll be waiting.
好的，我等你
"White. Male"
白种男人
"First name John."
名叫约翰…
"Last name 'G' for Gammell."
事实4：姓G…
"Drugs."
毒贩…
"License plate."
车牌
"SG1371U."
SG1371U
It's him.
是他
I found you, you fuck.
终于找到你这个贱人
You said we talked before. I don't remember that.
我记不得跟你谈过
Yeah, but it's not amnesia.
不是失忆症
I remember everything up until my injury. I just can't make new memories.
我只是记不得受伤以后的事
So I can't remember talking to you. What did we talk about?
我们谈过什么？
Oh, Sammy Jankis. I tell people about Sammy to help them understand.
谈杰克斯・萨米？因为杰克斯・萨米和我…
Sammy's story helps me understand my own situation.
都有短期失忆
Well, Sammy wrote himself endless amounts of notes,
萨米猛为自己写备忘字条
but he got mixed up.
不过他乱放字条
I have a more graceful solution to the memory problem.
我的方法更有效
I'm disciplined and organized.
我有条不紊
I use habit and routine to make my life possible.
所以能够应付日常生活
Sammy had no drive, no reason to make it work.
萨米没有推动力去帮自己记忆
Me?
我呢？
I got a reason.
我有推动力
"Today, 1:00 p.m. Meet Natalie for info.
今午一点见娜塔莉娅取消息
"She has also lost someone. She will help you out of pity."
她也失去爱人，会同情你、帮你
-Natalie? -You don't remember me.
-你是娜塔莉娅？ -你记不得我
I'm sorry. I should have explained. I have this...
对不起，我应该解释，我有…
You did explain, Lenny.
你解释过，莱尼
Please call me Leonard. My wife called me Lenny.
请叫我莱纳，我太太叫我莱尼
Yeah, I know. You told me.
我知道，你说过
Then I probably told you how much I hated it.
可能也说过讨厌叫莱尼
Do you mind taking your glasses off? It's hard for me to...
可以取下墨镜吗？
Thanks.
谢谢
So you have information for me?
你有消息给我？
Is that what your little note says?
你的字条那样写？
Must be tough living your life according to a couple of scraps of paper.
单靠字条生活，一定很辛苦
Mix your laundry list with your grocery list,
洗衣单和杂货单调乱
and you'll end up eating your underwear.
那就麻烦了
I guess that's why you have those freaky tattoos.
所以你甚至备忘纹在身上
Yeah, it's tough. It's almost impossible.
日子确实不好过
Look, I'm sorry I don't remember you. It's nothing personal.
记不得你，对不起，不要见怪
I do have information for you.
我的确有消息给你
You gave me a license plate number.
你给我个车牌
Had my friend at D.M.V. Trace it.
我去交通部查过
Guess what name came up.
猜猜是谁的
John Edward Gammell. John G.
约翰・爱德华・盖玛，约翰・G
Do you know him?
你认识他？
No, But his face on his driver's license looked really familiar.
不过照片上的人看起来很熟悉
I think he's been in the bar, maybe.
他可能来过酒吧
Here's a copy of his license, his registration, photo and all.
这是他车牌、照片副本
Are you sure you want this?
你真的要这样做？
-Have I told you what this man did? -Yeah.
-我有没有说过他做过什么？ -有
Then you shouldn't have to ask.
那你就不用问了
But even if you get revenge, you're not gonna remember it.
不过，你即使报了仇…
You're not even gonna know that it happened.
你也不会记得
My wife deserves vengeance.
妻子的仇不可不报
Doesn't make any difference whether I know about it.
记不记得无所谓
Just because there are things I don't remember
即使记不得
doesn't make my actions meaningless.
依然值得做
The world doesn't just disappear when you close your eyes, does it?
即使闭上眼睛，世界并没有消失
Anyway, maybe I'll take a photograph to remind myself,
我可以拍张照片来提醒自已
get another freaky tattoo.
或者再纹个备忘录在身上
Tell me about her again.
再说说她的事吧
Why?
为什么？
Because you like to remember her.
因为你喜欢记起她
She was beautiful.
她漂亮
-To me, she was perfect. -No.
对我来说，她是完美的
Don't just recite the words.
不要顺口说
Close your eyes... and remember her.
闭上眼睛去回忆她
You can just feel the details.
我可以感受到细节
The bits and pieces you never bothered to put into words.
一些平时懒得回忆的细节
And you can feel these extreme moments...
那些非常时刻…
even if you don't want to.
重现眼前
You put these together, and you get the feel of a person.
印像愈发清晰
Enough to know how much you miss them...
我更怀念她
and how much you hate the person who took them away.
也更痛恨凶手
I, um... I added an address in here.
我…我写了个地址在上面
It might be useful. It's an abandoned place outside of town.
也许有用，是近郊的一间荒屋
A guy I knew used to do bigger deals there.
我的朋友曾经在那里贩毒
It's isolated.
四周没有人
Sounds perfect.
好极了
Do I owe you any...
我应不应该付你…
I wasn't helping you for money.
不用，我不是为钱
I'm sorry.
对不起
It's okay. See, you have this condition.
不要紧，我知道你有病
Oh, are you still staying at the Discount Inn, room 304? You left it at my place.
还住在优惠旅馆？你遗留在我家
-They treating you okay? -I don't remember.
-旅馆招待好吗？ -我记不得
You know what we have in common?
你和我有个共同点
We are both survivors.
我们都懂得生存
You take care, Leonard.
保重，莱纳
"Remember Sammy Jankis."
记住杰克斯・萨米
I met Sammy through work. Insurance. I was an investigator.
我本来在保险公司服务
I'd investigate the claims to see which ones were phony.
负责调查保险索偿
I had to see through people's bullshit.
专长是辨别真与假
It was useful experience, 'cause now it's my life.
这专长现在派上大用场
When I meet someone, I don't know if I've met them before.
现在我靠观察去辨认…
I have to look in their eyes and try and figure them out.
眼前的人是不是相识的
My job taught me the best way to find out...
我知道
what someone knew was just to let them talk...
观言辨色…
and watch the eyes and the body language.
是了解人的最好办法
If someone scratches their nose while they're talking,
譬如，一边谈话一边擦鼻子…
experts tell you it means they're lying. It really means they're nervous.
那个人可能在说谎或者紧张
People get nervous for all sorts of reasons. It's all about context.
紧张的原因很多，视乎情形而定
Yeah, I was good.
对，我是观人高手
Sammy was my first real challenge.
第一个观察的人是萨米
Yo, Lenny!
莱尼！
I thought you split for good.
还以为你离开了本地
-Well, things change. -So I see.
-情况有变 -看得出来
My name's Teddy.
我叫泰迪
I guess I've told you about my condition.
我大概提到过我的病
Only every time I see you.
每次见面都提
Come on, I'll buy you lunch.
来，我请你吃午餐
-Have I told you about Sammy Jankis? -Mm. Yeah.
-我有没有提过杰克斯・萨米？ -有
I'm sick of hearing about the guy.
我听得好厌
What about John G? you think he still here?
约翰・G呢？你认为他还在？
-Who? -Johnny G., the guy you're looking for.
-谁？ -约翰・G，你要找的人
That's why you haven't left town, am I right?
你为了找他，才留在本地？
Maybe.
也许吧
Leonard, look, you have to be very careful.
莱纳，你非小心不可
Why?
为什么？
The other day you mentioned that maybe somebody was trying to set you up,
你提过有人想误导你…
get you to kill the wrong guy.
让你杀错人
Well, I go on facts, not recommendations, but thank you.
我会凭事实去判断
Lenny, you can't trust a man's life to your little notes and pictures.
怎能凭字条、照片去决定杀谁？
-Why not? -Because your notes could be unreliable.
-为什么不能？ -因为字条未必可靠
-Memory's unreliable. -Oh, please!
-记忆也未必可靠 -谢谢你的好心
No, really. Memory's not perfect. It's not even that good.
记忆不准确，甚至不合用
Ask the police.
问问警察吧
Eyewitness testimony is unreliable.
目击证供未必可靠
Cops don't catch a killer by remembering stuff.
警察不是凭记忆缉凶
Right...
我明白
They collect facts, they make notes, and they draw conclusions.
-警察搜集事实，做笔记，然后作出结沦 -那不是我的意思
Facts, not memories.
凭事实，不是凭记忙
That's how you investigate. It's what I used to do.
我以前是调查员，所以知道
Look, memory can change the shape of a room. It can change the color of a car.
形状、颜色等细节，未必记得准
And memories can be distorted.
可以记错
They're just an interpretation. They're not a record.
记忆只是一种演译，不是纪录
They're irrelevant if you have the facts.
掌握事实，就不用靠记忆
You really want to get this guy, don't you?
你非报仇不可？
He killed my wife. He took away my fucking memory.
他杀死我的妻子，夺去我的记忆
He destroyed my ability to live.
毁灭我生存的能力
You're living.
你还活着
Only for revenge.
完全为了报仇
Well, then we'll get the bastard.
那么我们把这坏蛋找出来
Where are you staying?
你住在哪里？
The Discount Inn.
特惠旅馆
I don't know what room. I haven't got my key.
我不知道是哪间房间，我没有钥匙
Probably left in in your room.
可能留在房里
I'm checked in here, but I think I've misplaced my key.
我是房客，不见了钥匙
How you doing, Leonard?
你好，莱纳
Probably in the room, right?
可能在房里
-I don't see my key anywhere. -This is the wrong room.
-我的钥匙呢？ -糟糕，进错房间了
-You're in 304 now. -I'm sorry. I fucked up.
-你现在住304号 -对不起，我搞错了
-This is not my room? -No.
-这不是我的房间？ -不是你的房间
Come on, let's go.
我们走吧
Why is this my handwriting?
为什么有我的笔迹？
This was your room, but now you're in 304.
以前是，现在你住304
-When was I in here? -Last week.
-我什么时候住过这间？ -上个星期
But then I rented you another room on top of it.
不过我再多租你一间
Why?
为什么？
Business is slow. I mean, I told my boss about the...
生意冷淡…你既然有这种病…
your condition and stuff, and he said try and rent him another room.
我们于是多租一间给你
So how many rooms am I checked into in this shit-hole?
我究竟租了几间？
Just two, so far.
只是两间，到目前为止
Well, at least you're being honest about ripping me off.
起码你坦白承认占我便宜
Well, you're not gonna remember anyway.
你反正不会记得
You don't have to be that honest, Burt.
用不着那样坦白
Leonard,
莱纳
always get a receipt.
每次都应该取收条
Oh, yeah. I'm gonna write that down.
我会记下来
-Hey, what time is it? -Quarter to one.
-现在几点了？ -12点45分
Excuse me.
对不起
Your room's...
你房间的…
-Natalie? -You don't remember me.
-娜塔莉娅 -你记不得我
I'd just become an investigator when I came across Sammy.
杰克斯・萨米的保险索赔…
Mr. Samuel R. Jankis. Strangest case ever.
十分奇特，是我接手的第一宗案子
Now, the guy's a 58-year-old semiretired accountant.
萨米58岁，半退休会计师
He and his wife had been in this car accident. Nothing too serious.
遇到交通意外，本来不算严重
But he's acting funny. He can't get a handle on what's going on.
奇怪的是，他记不住东西
The doctors find some possible damage to the hippocampus.
医生怀疑脑部受伤
Nothing conclusive,
但无法证实
but Sammy can't remember anything for more than a couple of minutes.
萨米的记忆只有几分钟
Can't work, can't do shit.
于是什么都不能做
The medical bills pile up. His wife calls the insurance company,
医药费昂贵，他的妻子通知了保险公司
and I get sent in.
公司派我调查
Now, this is my first big claims investigation, so I really check into it.
我初次查案，于是查得格外认真
Can I get you some coffee?
要不要咖啡？
Sammy can think just fine,
萨米思考没问题
but he can't make any new memories.
不过，他没有新记忆
-He can only remember things for a couple of minutes. -This is Mr. Shelby.
-只记得几分钟内的事 -这位是莱纳先生
He'd watch TV, but anything longer than a couple of minutes was too confusing.
他看电视，但过目则忘
He couldn't remember how it began.
记得后面的，却忘了前面的
He liked commercials. They were short.
他喜欢看广告，因为广告简短
Sammy. It's time for my shot.
萨米，到时间打针了
The crazy part was...
不可思议的是…
that this guy who couldn't even follow the plot of Green Acres anymore...
这个连电视也没法看的人…
could do the most complicated things...
却能够做复杂的事
as long as he learned them before the accident...
只要意外前学会的…
and as long as he kept his mind on what he was doing.
专心去做就行
Be gentle.
轻点
Now, the doctors assure me there's a real condition called anterial-grade...
医生说有一种罕有的病…
memory loss, or short-term memory loss. It's rare, but legit.
叫“杆脉失忆”，也就是短期失忆
Every time I see him...
不过，我每次见到他…
I catch this look,
从他的眼神…
this slight...
察觉…
look of recognition.
他好像有点认得我
But he says he can't remember me at all.
他却自称一点都认不得
Sammy, it's okay.
萨米，不要紧
I got it. I got it.
我开，我开
Hi, Mr. Shelby.
莱纳先生
Hi, Mrs. Jankis.
你好，杰克斯太太
This is Mr. Shelby, Sammy.
萨米，这位是莱纳先生
So now I'm suspicious, and I order more tests.
于是要求再做检验
Awake.
醒来
Oh, where am I?
我在哪里？
Somebody's bedroom.
某人的卧室
Ah, it must be her room.
一定是她的房间
But who is she?
不过，她是谁？
It's only me.
只是我
-Did you sleep okay? -Yeah. You?
-睡得好吗？ -好，你呢？
Oh, shit. Shit! I got to be someplace.
糟糕！我有地方要去
It's pretty weird.
相当怪异
It's useful. You never write a phone number on your hand?
你从不把电话写在手上？
I, um...
我…
I should be able to talk to my friend today...
我今天要去交通部…
about the license plate.
查查车牌的事
Yeah, the license plate.
对，车牌
John G.'s license plate.
约翰・G的车牌
You have it tattooed on your thigh.
你把车牌纹在你的大腿上
"Natalie."
娜塔莉娅
"She has also lost someone.
她也失去爱人
She will help you out of pity."
会同情你、帮你
If it's registered in this state,
只要是本州的车牌…
it should only take a couple of seconds to pull up his license and registration.
几秒钟就能查出车主资料
I'll call you as soon as I talk to him.
我一有资料就通知你
Do you think we could just arrange a meeting now?
不如现在就约定什么时候见面吧
I'm not too good on the phone.
很感谢你
You know, it's great that you...
多谢你…
well, that you're helping me like this.
这样…帮我
I'm helping you because you helped me.
我帮你，因为你帮过我
So next time you see me,
那么，下次见面…
will you remember me?
你会记得我吗？
I think you will.
我认为你会
I'm sorry.
对不起
Lenny, before you go, could I have my shirt back, please?
莱尼，可以把衣服还给我吗？
Yo, Lenny!
莱尼！
I thought you split for good.
还以为你离开了本地
Sammy couldn't pick up any new skills at all.
萨米不能够用一般的方法去学习
But I find something in my research: Conditioning.
不过，我认为他可以用惯性法
Sammy should still be able to learn through repetition.
重复又重复去学，一定能学会
It's how you learn stuff like riding a bike.
就像骑单车一样
You just get better through practice.
熟能生巧
It's a completely different part of the brain from the short-term memory.
没有短期记忆，也可以学会
So I had the doctors test Sammy's response to conditioning.
我请医生检验萨米对惯性的反应
Just pick up any three objects.
随便拣三件东西
That's a test?
这就算检验？
Hey, where were you guys when I did my C.P.A?
我考会计执照，遇上你们就好
Sorry.
对不起
-Ow! What the fuck? -It's a test, Sammy.
-搞什么？ -是检验，萨米
Well, test this, you fucking quack.
检验你个死人头
Some of the objects were electrified.
有几样通了电
They'd give him a small shock.
会让他稍微触电
They kept repeating the test, always with the same objects electrified.
通电的总是相同那几样
The point was...
目的是…
to see if Sammy could learn to avoid the electrified objects...
看看萨米能不能无须记忆…
not by memory, but by instinct.
单凭本能，去避开通电的
Natalie, right? Who the fuck is Dodd?
娜塔莉娅，是不是？这个该死的达德是谁？
Guess I don't have to worry about him anymore.
大概再不用理会他了
-What the fuck have you got me into? -Shh. Come inside.
-你给我惹了什么麻烦？ -进来吧
-Who is he? -Calm down.
-他是谁？ -冷静点
This is my problem.
这件事你主动帮我
It has nothing to do with your investigation.
跟你的调查没有关系
How did you get me into this?
你给我惹了什么麻烦？
You offered to help when you saw what he did to my face.
你知道他打伤我，就主动帮我
How do I know he did that?
我怎么知道他打你？
Because I came straight to you after he did it.
因为我告诉你
I showed you what he did, and I asked you to help me.
并请你帮忙
And I just take your word?
而我相信你的一面之词？
Something doesn't feel right.
不对
I think someone's fucking with me, trying to get me to kill the wrong guy.
有人愚弄我，想误导我去杀错人
-Did you? -What?
-你有没有？ -有没有什么？
-Kill him? -Of course not!
-杀他？ -当然没有！
Hey, what... Sit down, okay? Sit.
什么事嘛？坐下来
This has nothing to do with you.
这件事跟你无关
You helped me out, and I'm grateful.
你帮我，我很感激
You have to burn them.
要用火烧
Leonard, you decided to help me.
莱纳，你是自愿帮我的
Trust yourself. Trust your own judgment.
相信你自己吧，相信自己的判断
You can question everything. You can never know anything for sure.
不能够什么都怀疑
There are things you know for sure.
有些事情可以肯定
Such as?
比如呢？
I know what that's gonna sound like when I knock on it.
我敲一敲会有什么声音
I know what that's gonna feel like when I pick it up.
我捡起来会有什么感觉
See? Certainties.
所谓肯定…
It's the kind of memory you take for granted.
只是自以为错不了的记忆
You know,
我只有…
I can remember so much.
未受伤前的记忆
The feel of the world...
主要是…
and her.
关于她
She's gone.
她已经不在人世
And the present is trivia, which I scribble down as fucking notes!
我现在只能靠写字条过日子
Hey, hey, come on. Try and relax. Come on.
不要焦急，放松
It's not easy for me to relax, you know? Shh.
放松不容易
Come on. Take your jacket off.
脱掉外衣吧
Yeah. Come on.
脱吧
Didn't think you were the type.
想不到你是那种人
It's backwards.
是反转的
Come here.
过来
What about here?
这里呢？
Maybe it's for when I find him.
也许等到找到他的时候
I've lost somebody too.
我也失去过爱人
I'm sorry.
一定很难过
His name was Jimmy.
他叫杰米
What happened to him?
发生什么事？
He went to meet somebody. He never came back.
他去见人，一去不回
Who did he go to meet?
见谁？
A guy called Teddy.
一个叫泰迪的人
What do the police think?
警察找不到他？
They don't look too hard for guys like Jimmy.
警察不会理会杰米那种人
When you find this guy, This...
你找到那个…
John G., what are you gonna do?
约翰・G，打算怎样？
I'm gonna kill him.
我要杀掉他
Maybe I can help you find him.
我也许可以帮你找
I don't even know how long she's been gone.
我不知道她起床了多久
It's like I've woken up in bed and she's not here...
我醒来时，她已经不在
because she's gone to the bathroom or something.
大概是上了洗手间吧
But somehow I just...
不过，总觉得…
I just know she's never gonna come back to bed.
她不会再回到床上来
If I could just...
假如我能够…
reach over and touch her side of the bed...
伸手过去，摸摸她那边的床…
I would know that it was cold.
就会知道是冷的
But I can't.
不过，我不能
I know I can't have her back.
我知道她不会再回来
But I don't want to wake up in the morning thinking she's still here.
我不想早上醒来，以为她还在
I lie here...
我独自躺在这里…
not knowing how long I've been alone.
不知道躺了多久
So how...
那么…
How can I heal?
我怎么能够康复？
How am I supposed to heal if I can't...
感觉不到时间…
"She has also lost someone.
她也失去了爱人
She will help you out of pity."
会同情你、帮你
They kept testing Sammy for months,
他们检验了萨米几个月
always with the same objects carrying an electrical charge.
通电的总是相同的几样
Ow! What the fuck?
搞什么鬼？
It's a test, Sammy.
是检验，萨米
Test this, you quack!
验你个死人头
Even with total short-term memory loss,
萨米即使完全短期失忆…
Sammy should have learned to instinctively
应该能够靠本能
stop picking up the wrong objects.
避免捡错物件
All the previous cases responded to conditioning.
谁都能靠惯性去学习
Sammy didn't respond at all. It was enough to suggest...
萨米完全不能，于是证实…
that his condition
他所患的是心理病
was psychological, not physical.
不是生理病
We turned down his claim on the grounds that he wasn't covered for mental illness.
保险不保心理，我们拒绝赔偿
His wife got stuck with the bills, and I got a big promotion.
医药费由杰克斯太太负担，我升职
Conditioning didn't work for Sammy, so he became helpless.
惯性对萨米起不了作用
But it works for me.
对我却有效
I live the way Sammy couldn't.
我不像萨米
Habit and routine make my life possible.
我能够靠习惯而生活
Conditioning.
靠惯性
Acting on instinct.
靠本能
Awake.
一觉醒来
Where am I?
我在哪里？
Motel room.
旅馆房间里
Some anonymous motel room.
某家旅馆房间里
Nothing in the drawers,
虽然抽屉空空如也
but I'll take a look anyway.
我还是要打开来看看
Nothing except the Gideon Bi...
只有一本基甸社送的…
Bible.
圣经
Hey, open up!
开门
Just a minute.
等一等
Lenny!
莱尼？
Open the door!
开门
Come on!
快开门
Hi, Teddy.
泰迪
Finished playing with yourself, Lenny?
你玩够了没有？
Oh, I get it. Amorous neighbors.
我明白了，隔壁有人在亲热
What are you doing here?
你来做什么？
You called me.
是你叫我来的
You said you needed my help.
你说要我帮忙
You know, I've had more rewarding friendships than this one.
我是看在朋友的份上才帮你的
Although I do get to keep telling the same jokes.
虽然总是得忍受你一遍遍地唠叨
What the fuck is that?
怎么回事？
-Who the fuck is that? -You don't know him?
-是谁？ -你不认识？
No! Should I?
不认识，我应该认识？
Wait a minute. Is that John G?
等一等，是不是约翰・G？
I don't think so.
相信不是
You don't think so? You didn't write it down?
你没有记下来？
-I might've fallen asleep. -For Christ's sakes!
-我还没记就睡着了 -真离谱
Ask him.
问他吧
What's your name? Your name!
你叫什么？
-Dodd. -And who did this to you?
-达德 -谁打伤了你？
-What? -Who did this to you?
-什么？ -谁打伤了你？
You did.
你
Look, I'm not gonna help you kill that guy.
我不会帮你杀人
No, just let me think for a minute.
不，让我想想
-Okay, Natalie. -Who's Natalie?
娜塔莉娅，谁是娜塔莉娅？
-Natalie who? -Why?
-哪个娜塔莉娅？ -为什么问？
Maybe I know her.
说不定我认识她
Look, we gotta get him out of here.
我们要把他弄走
He's gotta have a car, right?
他一定有车
So we take him down to his car,
送他上车
we tell him to get out of town or we're gonna kill him.
然后吓跑他
We can't just walk him out of here tied up and bleeding.
他在流血，怎么出去？
-How the fuck did you get him up here? -I don't know!
-他怎样上来的？ -不知道
You don't know.
你不知道？
Yes, I do. This is not my room.
我知道这不是我的房间
It must be his room. Great! Let's go.
一定是他的，我们自己走吧
We can't just leave him here.
不可以把他留在这里
Why not?
为什么？
The maid's gonna walk in. She'll see him, call the cops. He can I.D. Us.
女工发现，会报警，他认得我们
Okay. We untie him, we clean him up...
先替他松绑、清理
and we march him out of here with a gun in his back.
然后用枪押走
A gun. Why would I have a gun?
枪？哪里有枪
It must be his. I don't think they'd let someone like me carry a gun.
一定是他的，我这种人不会有枪
Fucking hope not.
你有枪就不得了
Which one?
哪一部？
We should probably steal his car. You know, teach him a lesson.
不如偷了他的车，作为惩戒
Shut up.
住口
That's all right for you to say. You're the one with the Jag.
你开着美州豹，当然不想偷
All right, get in.
好，上车
I'm gonna ride with him. You follow us.
我载他，你随后来
Give me your keys.
把你的车匙拿来
Take your own car.
你开自己的车吧
So was he scared?
他害怕吗？
-Yeah. I think it was your sinister moustache. -Fuck you.
-他怕你那撇小胡子 -扯蛋
You should have stolen his car.
你应该偷他的车
What's wrong with this one?
这辆有什么不好？
Nothing. You want to trade?
你想交换吗？
So what do you do now?
你打算怎么样？
I'm going to find out what the fuck that was all about.
我要查个清楚
Natalie, right? Who the fuck is Dodd?
娜塔莉娅，是不是？这个该死的达德是谁？
Sammy's wife was crippled by the cost of supporting him...
萨米的妻子要负担…
and fighting the company's decision.
丈夫沉重的医药费
But it wasn't the money that got to her.
不过，她耿耿于怀的不是钱
I never said that Sammy was faking.
我没说过萨米在假装
Listen. I have an idea. Sammy,
萨米…
Sammy, I have an idea I want you to do for me.
我想你替我办一件事
Just that his problem was mental, not physical.
我只说是心理病，不是生理病
I want you to have a pen in your pocket, okay?
我要你把这支笔装到口袋里
You're gonna have a pen in your pocket.
你口袋里得有支笔
She couldn't understand.
而是不明白丈夫的病况
I did something wrong.
记事簿
You did something wrong!
你没有做错什么
We're gonna deal with it.
你当然做错了，我们得想想办法
When she looks into his eyes and sees the same person. If it's not a physical problem,
她觉得，假如自己的丈夫…
he should just snap out of it.
患的不是生理病，应该可以痊愈
-Ellen called! -Ellen called?
-爱伦打过电话来 -爱伦打过电话来
Ellen can't come today! Ellen can't come!
爱伦今天不能来，爱伦今天…
I'm sorry. I'm trying. I'm sorry.
很对不起！我已经尽了力！
Try harder!
要更加努力！
So good old Leonard Shelby
我让她怀疑…
from the insurance company gives her the seed of doubt...
丈夫患心理病
just like he gave it to the doctors.
就像我让医生怀疑一样
But I never said that he was faking. I never said that.
我从未说过他假装
Hmm, I don't feel drunk.
我不觉得喝醉过
Hello? Housekeeping.
喂
Oh, shit.
糟糕！
-Not right now. -Oh, I'm sorry.
-现在不方便 -对不起
"Dodd. Put him onto Teddy or just get rid of him for Natalie."
为娜塔莉娅收拾达德，叫泰迪帮忙
Dodd.
达德
Get rid of him.
收拾他
Ask Natalie.
问娜塔莉娅
Teddy, Teddy.
泰迪、泰迪
Yeah, leave your number. You know what to do.
请留下你的电话号码
Yeah. This is a message for Teddy.
泰迪
I'm at the Mountcrest Inn of Fifth Street, room six.
我在顶峰旅馆，6号房
I need you to come over as soon as you get this.
请尽快来
It's important. Oh, this is Leonard. Thanks. Bye.
很重要，我是莱纳，拜拜
Whew. Fuck.
妈的
Mrs. Jankis didn't understand
杰克斯太太不明白
that you can't bully someone into remembering.
记忆是强逼不来的
The more pressure you're under, the harder it gets.
施压只有弄巧反拙
Uh, well, then call me... call me back?
给我打电话，好吗？
Okay, so what am I doing?
我在做什么？
Oh, I'm chasing this guy.
我在追这个人
No. He's chasing me.
不，他在追我
Fuck.
妈的
"Dodd. White guy. Mountcrest Inn on Fifth Street."
达德，白种人、顶峰旅馆
I'll get the jump on you, you fucker.
我不会放过你，贱种
$9995, $98 a month.
9995美金，月供98美金
A '97 Toyota RAV-4, $ 11,995, $ 110 a month.
97款丰田RAV-4，11，995美金 月供110美金
-Oh, fuck. -A '96 Dodge Caravan, $8995, $95 a month.
-妈的 -96款道奇客货车，8995美金，月供95美金
-Sorry. -A '97...
-对不起 -97款…
I need a weapon.
我需要武器
This will do.
这件合用
Hmm, I don't feel drunk.
我不觉得喝醉过
Do I know this guy?
我认识他吗？
He seems to know me.
他好像认识我
What the fuck?
什么回事？
-I like your car. -Thank you.
-我喜欢你的这辆车 -谢谢
Where'd you get it?
在哪里买的？
Are you interested in buying one?
你有兴趣买？
What, I haven't made a strong enough impression on you?
你觉得我不起眼？
I wouldn't be too hard on yourself.
不用太自卑
Okay, so what am I doing?
我在做什么？
Who is this?
谁？
Ouch. Cut it out.
继续
How can you read that again?
你怎么可以读完又读？
It's good.
好看嘛
Yeah, but you've read it, like, a thousand times.
你似乎读过上千次
I enjoy it.
我喜欢读
I always thought the pleasure of a book...
读小说
was in wanting to know what happens next.
不知道下文才有趣
Look, don't be a prick.
不要那样扫兴
I'm not reading it to annoy you. I enjoy it.
我完全因为喜欢读而读
Just let me read, please.
让我读下去，好不好？
Probably tried this before.
可能以前烧过
Probably burned truckloads of your stuff.
可能已经烧掉你很多遗物
Can't remember to forget you.
总是忘不了你
Yeah.
是
Well, sir, that'd certainly be in keeping with some of my own discoveries.
情况跟我所掌握的资料一致
I was hoping for a little more on the drugs angle. Hang on a sec?
我希望多了解毒品方面的事
Now, the police report mentioned
警方报告提到
the drugs found in the car outside my house.
凶手车里有毒品
The car was stolen. Bloody prints were all over it.
车是失窃的，车上遍布凶手的指纹
I got friends in the department. They gave me a copy of it.
我认识一位警察，报告是他给我的
I dealt with the police a lot in my insurance job.
我做保险，有机会认识警察
With my condition, it's really tough. I can't...
因为我这个病…
keep it all in mind at once.
我没法记得整份报告
I have to summarize the different sections.
只好记要紧的
And there's pages missing.
报告有几页不见了
I guess I've been trying to log them all.
并不完整
I don't know why these are crossed out.
有部分被删除掉，奇怪
But they weren't even looking for John G.
不过，警方并不追缉约翰・G
The stuff they found in the car just fit in with what they believed had happened,
认为没有必要
so they didn't chase any of it up.
不了了之
Honey.
亲爱的
Honey, it's late.
亲爱的，很晚了
Everything okay?
没事吧？
You okay in there?
你没事吧？
Was it good for you?
满意吗？
What? Was I supposed to lock the door?
什么？要我锁门？
No.
不用
I'd like you to leave now.
你走吧
There's something about the drugs stashed in the car that doesn't ring true for me.
凶手车里有毒品，是个关键
Because the police claim the guy was an addict,
警方说凶手是吸毒的
needing money to score, which I think is bullshit,
打劫我家，是为了有钱买毒品
'cause he's not gonna go breaking into places
他已经有大批毒品
while he's still got a stash that big.
还用打劫？
Well, I think John G. Left it there
我认为约翰・G…
or planted it there.
用毒品栽赃嫁货
How do you know that?
你怎么知道？
Oh, shit, that's true. It fits.
对了，怪不得
So he's a dealer.
那么他是毒贩了
Hang on a sec.
等一等
Now we're getting somewhere.
现在有头绪了
"Discount Inn."
特惠旅馆
Yeah, OK. Blonde's fine.
金发女郎，好
Well, that's what they say.
对了
The Discount Inn. 304.
特惠旅馆，304号房间
Leonard.
我叫莱纳
Well, what then?
想怎么样？
We just go to bed. You wait for me to fall asleep.
我们上床，你等我睡着
You go into the bathroom and you slam the door.
然后上厕所，用力关门
Slam it?
用力关门？
Yeah. Loud enough to wake me up.
用力到吵醒我
-And that's it? -That's it.
-只是这样吗？ -只是这样
yeah, first I just need you to put these things around the room.
先把这些东西四处放
Just pretend they're your things and that this is your bedroom.
假装是你的东西、你的卧室
Should I wear it?
要我穿上去吗？
No, no, no. Uh, just like you took it off or something.
不用，就好像你刚刚脱下来
I-I don't want you to use it. I'm sorry.
我不要你用，对不起
Just... I just mean put them around the room, you know,
只要你随便放在房里
as if they were your... your things.
就像是你的…你的东西
Whatever gets you off.
你喜欢怎么样就怎么样好了
I can't blame the cops for not taking me seriously.
我不怪警方不理会
This is difficult to understand.
我的病不容易明白
I mean, look at Sammy Jankis.
看看杰克斯・萨米吧
His own wife couldn't deal with it.
杰克斯太太实在受不了
I told you about how she tried to get him to snap out of it.
怎么都不能让他恢复记忆
Eventually she came to see me at the office. I found out all kinds of shit.
她终于来办公室见我
She told me about life with Sammy, how she treated him.
说用尽办法强逼萨米记忆
Thank you for seeing me.
谢谢你见我
It got to the point where she'd get Sammy
甚至要萨米
to hide food all around the house...
把食物收藏起来
and then she'd stop feeding him just to see if his hunger...
要他记着收藏地点
would make him remember where he'd hidden the food.
否则就挨饿
She wasn't a cruel person. She just wanted old Sammy back.
她不是狠心，只是希望萨米康复
Mr. Shelby, you know all about Sammy and you've decided that he's faking.
你认为萨米在假装
Mrs. Jankis, the company's position isn't that Sammy is faking anything.
公司并没有说萨米假装
It's just that his condition can't be shown to be...
只是认为他的病不是…
I just wanna know what your honest opinion about Sammy is.
我只想知道你的真正看法
We shouldn't even be talking like this while the case is still open to appeal.
案件在上诉，我们不应该讨论
I'm not appealing the decision.
我不会提出上诉
Then why are you here?
那么你想怎么样？
Try to understand. When I look at Sammy,
当我看到萨米
I don't see some... vegetable.
我看的不是植物人
I see my same old Sammy.
而是以前的萨米
What do you think that's like for me...
我总是抱有希望
to suspect that he might be imagining this whole problem?
总希望他完全是心理作祟
And that if I just could say the right thing,
总希望有办法…
he'd snap out of it and go back to being normal.
让他痊愈
If I...
如果…
If I knew that my old Sammy were truly gone,
萨米确实无可药救，那么…
then I could say good-bye and start loving this new Sammy.
我会抛开过去，爱现在的萨米
As long as I have doubt, I can't say good-bye and move on.
一天抱有希望，一天就死心不息
What do you want from me?
你要我怎么样？
I want you to forget the company you work for for 30 seconds...
我要你撇开公事半分钟
and tell me if you really believe that Sammy's faking his condition.
告诉我萨米是不是假装
I need to know...
我需要知道…
what you honestly believe.
你真正的想法
I believe that Sammy should be physically capable of making new memories.
我相信萨米有记忆能力
I thought I helped her.
我以为帮了她
I thought she just needed some kind of answer.
以为她只是要一个答案
I didn't think it was important what the answer was,
以为什么答案都不重要
just that she had one to believe.
以为她只要一个可信的答案
A car this nice you should lock.
这样好的车，你应该上锁
-Who the fuck are you? -Teddy, your buddy.
-你是谁！ -你的朋友泰迪
Prove it.
证明一下！
Sammy. Remember Sammy? You told me about Sammy!
你告诉过我萨米的事
What the fuck are you doing in my car?
你在我车内干什么？
What, your sense of humor went with the memory?
你连幽默感也忘掉？
Do you even know why you're here?
你为什么在这里，知道吗？
Unfinished business.
有未了结的事
Lenny,
莱尼
let me inform you. Your business here is very much finished.
告诉你吧，你的事已经了结
You're still here because of Natalie.
你为了娜塔莉娅，所以还在这里
Who's Natalie?
谁是娜塔莉娅？
Schmuck, whose house do you think you just walked out of?
傻瓜，你刚从谁的家走出来？
Oh, that's right. Take a look at your pictures.
对，看看照片吧
I bet you got one of her.
你肯定有她的照片
Oh, nice shot, Leibovitz.
拍得好啊，大摄影师
You'll wanna make a note.
记下来吧
You can't trust her.
不要相信她
Oh, yeah? Why's that?
为什么？
Because by now she's taken a look at this suit and the car...
因为她看出你有钱…
and she's starting to figure out ways of turning the situation to her advantage.
打算利用你，捞点油水
She's already got you staying with her, for Christ's sakes.
她已经把你搭上手了
You can't go back in there.
你不可以回她的家
Let me give you the name of a motel.
我介绍你入住间旅馆吧
You're lucky I ran into you. That broad's bad news.
碰到我，算你运气好
What do you mean, "bad news"?
那女的为什么碰不得？
She's involved with drugs.
她涉及毒品
All right, look. These. You see these?
看到吗？
This is the bar where she works.
这是她服务的酒吧
Her boyfriend's a drug dealer.
她的男朋友是毒贩
She takes orders for him, arranges meets.
她替他办事，传递消息
He writes messages on the back of these.
他把讯息写在纸的背后
Then she slips him the answers when she serves him his drinks.
她趁斟酒时给他，偷偷替他传递
Why should I care?
关我什么事？
Because when she gets jammed up,
因为她惹上了麻烦…
she's gonna use you to protect herself.
打算利用你来替她解决
From who?
谁想找她的麻烦？
Guys are gonna wanna know what happened to her boyfriend.
想知道她男朋友下落的人
Guys are gonna come after her. Somebody's gotta pay, Lenny.
那人要找她出气．总有人受罪
Somebody always pays.
一定有人受罪
Maybe she'll make it you.
也许她想用你来挡灾
-Oh, yeah? -Well, maybe she'll make it you.
-是吗？ -也许她想利用你来挡灾
Is that it?
是不是？
You worried that she's gonna use me against you?
你担心她利用我来对付你
-No. -Why not?
为什么不会？
Because she doesn't know who I am.
因为她不认识我
-Why are you following me? -Maybe I wanna help.
-你为什么跟着我？ -也许我想帮你
She doesn't know anything about your investigation,
她完全不知道你在调查什么
okay, Einstein? So write this down.
天才，记下来吧
When she offers to help, it'll be for her own reasons.
她提议帮你，其实是为了自已
I'm not lying. Take my pen. Write this down.
我没有骗你，用我这支笔记下来
Do not trust her.
不要相信她
There. You happy now?
现在高兴了没有？
I won't be happy until you leave town.
你离开本地我才高兴
Why not?
为什么？
You ever wonder how long you can hang around here
你留下来
before people start asking questions?
迟早有人会问
What sort of questions?
问什么？
The same sort of questions you should be asking yourself.
问你自己应该问的问题
Like what?
例如呢？
Like, how did you get this suit, the car?
你为什么穿着名牌西服？开着名牌车？
-I have money. -From what?
-我有钱 -从哪里来？
My wife's death.
我太太去世了
I used to work in insurance. We were well covered.
我以前在保险公司工作，所以买足了保险
So in your grief you wandered into a Jaguar dealership.
你痛失娇妻，于是去买美州豹？
You don't have a clue, do you?
回答不出来吧
-You don't even know who you are. -Yes, I do.
-你连自已是谁都不知道 -我知道
I don't have amnesia.
我没有失忆
I remember everything right up until the incident.
意外前的事我统统记得
I am Leonard Shelby. I am from San Francisco...
我叫莱纳・谢尔比，旧金山人
That's who you were.
那是以前的身份
You do not know who you are,
你不知道现在的身份
what you've become since...
意外发生后…
the incident.
你变成怎么样的人
You wander around playing detective.
你到处扮侦探
You don't even know how long ago it was.
连扮了多久都不知道
Let me put it this way.
让我问问你
Were you wearing designer suits when you sold insurance?
你推销保险，够钱穿名牌西装
-I didn't sell insurance. I investigated it. -Right.
-不是推销，是调查 -对
You're an investigator.
你是调查员
Well, maybe you should start investigating yourself.
你预先应该调查自已
Thank you for the advice.
谢谢你的忠告
Look, do me a favor. Don't go back in there.
帮个忙，不要回到她家去
Will you take the motel out of town?
住旅馆好不好？
It's been fun, Lenny.
拜拜，莱尼
"Do not trust her."
不要相信她
"Don't believe his lies."
不要受他的骗
Oh, fuck it. I need my own place.
算了，我自己租房住
No. She shouldn't have given me that responsibility.
杰克斯太太不应该逼我回答那种问题
I'm a claims investigator, not a doctor.
我是保险调查员，不是医生
Yeah, yeah. I guess.
对
But I've got all sorts of other considerations.
我有很多顾虑
Legal responsibility, large financ...
法律责任、大笔的赔款…
Who is this?
谁？
Write this down. Write down what happened.
记下来，记下所发生的事情
Write it down. Write it down. Come on. Concentrate. Keep it in mind. Find a pen...
记下来，集中精神，记着
What happened?
什么事？
What does it look like? He beat the shit out of me.
还用问？他打我
Who?
谁？
Fuck, Leonard. Dodd. Dodd beat the shit out of me.
达德啊！达德打我
-Why? -Why? Because of you.
-为什么？ -为什么？都是你
-Because I did what you told me to do! -Calm down.
我照你的吩咐，去找他
Tell him about Teddy! Great fucking idea!
告诉他泰迪的事，结果挨打！
Calm down. Take it easy.
冷静点
You're safe. It's okay.
不要怕
Come on. Just sit down.
坐下来
Sit down.
坐
Okay. You're okay.
不要怕
I'll just get some ice for your face.
我拿些冰来给你敷脸
I did exactly what you told me to do.
我按照你的吩咐去做
I went to Dodd...
我去找达德
and I told him that I... I didn't have any of Jimmy's money...
告诉他杰米的钱、毒品…
or the drugs,
都不在我身上
and that this Teddy must have taken everything.
肯定统统被那个泰迪拿掉
And what did he say?
他怎么说的？
He didn't believe me.
他不相信我
He said if I don't have the drugs by tomorrow, he's gonna kill me.
限我明天交出毒品，否则就杀我
And then he just... he just started hitting me.
说完了就打我
Where is he?
他在哪里？
Why?
为什么问？
I'll go see him.
我要去见他
And?
然后呢？
I'll give him some bruises of his own and tell him to look for a guy called Teddy.
打他，叫他去找泰迪
Ah, he'll kill you, Lenny.
他会杀了你的，莱尼
-My wife used to call me Lenny. -Yeah?
-我太太叫我莱尼 -是吗？
Yeah. I hated it.
我讨厌莱尼这个名字
Oh, this guy... this guy is so dangerous.
达德这个人惹不得
Let's just think of something else, okay?
我们另想办法吧
No, no. You just tell me what he looks like...
告诉我他的模样…
and where I can find him.
哪里能找到他就行了
Have you got a pen?
你有笔吧？
In my purse.
在手袋内
He'll, um... He'll probably find you.
他…他也许会找你
What do you mean?
什么意思？
I told him about your car.
我告诉他你的车
Why?
为什么？
He was beating the shit out of me. I had to tell him something.
我挨不住打，只好说点东西
Just write it all down.
写下来吧
Be careful.
小心
I'll be fine.
不用担心
A car this nice you should lock.
这样名贵的车，你应该上锁
Who the fuck are you?
你是谁？
Front desk? Burt. Right. This is Mr. Shelby in room 21.
柜台吗？我是21号房的莱纳
Yeah, that's it. I don't want any calls.
对，我不要接听电话
Nope. None at all.
对，什么电话都不听
-What's wrong? -Somebody's come already.
-什么事？ -有人来过
-Who? -He calls himself Dodd.
-是谁？ -他自称达德
What does he want?
什么？
He wants to know what happened to Jimmy and his money.
追问杰米和他的钱的下落
He thinks I have it. He thinks I took it.
他以为我私吞了
Oh. Well, did you?
你有没有？
No.
没有
-What's this all about? -Fuck!
-怎么回事？ -妈的
You don't have a fucking clue, do you?
你什么都不知道
You're just blissfully ignorant.
你…你无知得相当舒服
Look, I have this condition.
我有种病
Yeah, I know all about your fucking condition, Leonard!
我知道你的病
Probably know more about it than you do.
我可能比你更清楚
You don't have a clue about anything else.
你什么都不知道
What happened?
什么事？
Jimmy went to meet some guy named Teddy.
杰米去了见一个叫泰迪的人
He took a lot of money with him, and he never came back.
他拿了很多钱去，一去不返
Jimmy's partners think I set him up.
杰米的拍档以为我是合谋
I don't even know if you know this, Teddy, or how well.
我连你认不认识泰迪都不知道
-Neither do I. -Don't protect him!
-我也不知道 -不要维护他！
I'm not.
我没有维护他
-Help me. -How?
-帮帮我 -怎么帮？
Get rid of Dodd for me.
替我铲除达德
What?
什么？
Kill him. I'll pay you.
杀掉他，我付你钱
What do you think I am? I'm not gonna kill someone for money.
什么？我不会为钱杀人
What then? Love? What would you kill for?
那么为什么？为爱？
You'd kill for your wife, wouldn't you?
你肯为太太杀人
That's different.
那是另一回事
Not to me. I wasn't fucking married to her.
对我是同一回事
Hey, don't talk about my wife.
不要谈我太太
I can talk about whoever the fuck I want!
我要谈谁，就谈谁
I can say whatever I want and you won't remember.
无论我说什么，你都记不得
I could call your wife a fucking whore.
骂你老婆是婊子，我们还可以做朋友
Calm down.
冷静点
Easy for you to say. You can't get scared. You don't know how, you fucking idiot!
你是白痴，根本不识死
Take it easy. This has nothing to do with me.
不要冲动，这事跟我无关
Maybe it does.
可能有关！
How the fuck would you know?
你怎么知道无关？
You don't know a fucking thing!
你不识死
-You can't get scared, but can you get angry? -Yes.
-不过会生气？ -会！
Ah, you pathetic piece of shit.
你这个该死的猪
I can say whatever the fuck I want...
无论我说什么…
and you won't have a fucking clue, you fucking retard!
你都莫名其妙，死蠢材
-Shut your mouth. -You know what?
-住口 -知不知道？
I'm gonna use you.
我会利用你
I'm telling you now, because I'm gonna enjoy it so much more...
我声明会利用你，你这个神经病…
if I know that you could stop me if you weren't such a fucking freak.
照样会给我利用
Did you lose your pen?
你丢掉了笔？
Well, that's too bad, freak.
太倒霉了，神经病
Otherwise, you could write yourself a little note about how much Natalie...
否则你会记下娜塔莉娅…
hates your retarded guts and that I called your wife a whore.
恨透你了，同时认为你老婆是个婊子
Don't say another fuckin' word.
不准再说！
About your whore of a wife?
不准再说什么？你老婆是婊子？
I read about your condition, Leonard.
据说短期失忆…
You know what one of the causes of short-term memory loss is?
这种病，其中一个成因…
Venereal disease.
是性病
Maybe your cunt of a fucking wife...
也许你的淫贱老婆…
sucked one too many diseased cocks
搞过有性病的男人，传染给你
and turned you into a fucking retard!
把你传染成白痴！
You sad, sad... freak.
死神经病！
I can say whatever the fuck I want...
我想说什么就说什么
and you won't remember.
你不会记得
We'll still be best friends...
我们依然做好朋友
or maybe even lovers.
甚至做情人
Fuck.
妈的
I'll see you soon.
再见
Stay focused. Find a pen. Gotta write this down.
集中精神，找支笔记下来
Gotta write it down.
记下来
Concentrate. Concentrate. Concentrate.
集中精神…
Keep it in mind. Keep it in mind. Keep it in mind.
记住、记住…
Come on. Find a pen. I have to find a pen.
找支笔，我要找支笔
Write this down.
记下来
Write this down, exactly what happened.
统统记下来
Gonna write down exactly what happened.
记下所发生的事情
Come on. Come on. Come on. Find a pen. Jeez! Come on.
快点！我要找支笔！
Okay, focus. Keep focused.
集中精神
Keep... Keep it in mind.
记住
Come on. Find a pen. Write this note.
快找支笔，记下来
Write down what happened. Write it down. Write it down. Come on.
记下所发生的事情
Concentrate. Keep it in mind. Find a pen.
集中精神，记住，找支笔
What happened?
发生了什么事？
What does it look like? He beat the shit out of me.
还用问？他打我
Who?
谁？
Fuck, Leonard. Dodd. Dodd beat the shit out of me.
达德啊！达德打我
It's Burt, from the front desk.
我是柜台的波特
I know you said you didn't want any calls.
你吩咐过不接电话
But this guy called. He's on the phone now. He says he's a cop.
可是这个人自称警察
-A cop? -Yeah.
警察？
And, uh, he says you're really gonna wanna know what he has to say, so...
他说…他有你要的资料
I'm not too good on the phone.
我不喜欢讲电话
I need to look people in the eye when I talk to them.
我要面对面谈
Well, what...
那么…怎样了？
You can, um... You can crash on the couch.
去沙发歇歇吧
It's comfortable.
会很舒服的
Just have a seat.
坐吧
So how long do you think it's gonna take you?
你认为需要多久？
You told me you were looking for the guy who killed your wife?
多久才找得到杀妻仇人？
Oh, well, that depends on if he's here in town or if he's moved on.
要看他是在本地还是在外地
I have my file here.
我有他的资料
Can I ask you something?
让我问问你
If you have all of that information,
你既然资料齐全…
then why haven't the police found him for you?
为什么警方不替你缉凶？
-Well, they're not looking for him. -Why not?
-警方不肯缉凶 -为什么？
They don't think he exists.
他们认为已经没有凶手
You see, I told them what I remembered.
我把经过告诉了他们
I was asleep.
我正在睡觉
Something woke me up.
突然醒来
Her side of the bed was cold. She'd obviously been out of bed for awhile.
她的床是凉的，下了床相当久
There had to be a second man.
肯定有第二个凶手
Somebody hit me from behind.
他从后袭击我
I remember. It's about the last thing that I do remember.
此后，我什么都不记得
Look, the police did not believe me. If we check the police...
警方不相信有第二个凶手
How do they explain what you do remember?
警方怎么解释案情？
The gun and stuff.
怎么解释枪和其他？
John G. Was clever.
约翰・G很狡猾
He was clever.
很狡猾
See, he took the dead man's gun
他拿掉死者的枪
and replaced it with the sap that he hit me with.
换上袭击过我的棍子
He left my gun and he left the getaway car.
留下我的枪和贼车
He gave the police a complete package.
于是误导了警方
The found the sap with my blood on it in the dead man's hand.
警方在死者手中的棍子上发现我的血迹
And they only found my gun.
并且只找到我的枪
They didn't need to look for anybody else.
于是断定只有一个凶手
I was the only guy who disagreed with the facts, and I had brain damage.
我认为有第二个，可是我伤了脑子
-See, the cops are not gonna believe someone in my condition. -Leonard,
警方不会相信有脑病的人
You can stay here for a couple of days if it'll help you.
你可以在这里住几天
I have to go back to work.
我要上班去
So, um, just make yourself at home. You can watch TV, or...
不用客气，随便看电视
you can have some food, whatever you want, okay?
随便吃东西
Make yourself at home.
不用客气
One thing.
一件事
Something to remember you by.
我想记得你
My name is Natalie.
我叫娜塔莉娅
"Natalie."
娜塔莉娅
-What's wrong? -Somebody's come already.
-什么事？ -有人来过
On the house.
免费
My, you really do have a problem.
你确实有问题
Just like that cop said.
正如警察所说的一样
Your condition.
你有病
Well, nobody's perfect.
没有人十全十美
What's the last thing that you do remember?
你最后记得的是什么？
My wife.
我太太
That's sweet.
真是多情
Dying.
垂死…
I remember my wife dying.
我太太垂死的情形
Let me, um, get you another one.
我替你换杯子
I think this one's dusty.
这个杯子有灰尘
-Why are you calling me? -What do you want?
-你为什么找我？ -要什么？
I know you're a cop, but what do you want?
我知道你是警察
Have I done something wrong?
我犯了法？
I don't know. Something bad, maybe.
做了坏事？
Why are you asking me? I can't remember what I've done.
为什么问我？我记不得
You wouldn't believe me anyway.
你反正不会相信
Because of my condition. You don't believe someone with this condition.
你不会相信我有这种病
Nobody believed Sammy! I didn't even fucking believe Sammy!
就像我不相信萨米一样！
"Ferdy's Bar."
费迪斯酒吧
"Come by after. Natalie."
下班来，娜塔莉娅
I'll have a beer, please.
啤酒，麻烦你
-What do you want? -A beer, please.
-要什么？ -啤酒，麻烦你
You can't just waltz in here dressed like that and ask for a beer.
你穿成那模样来喝啤酒？
-What, is there a dress code? -Why are you here?
-你们有服装规定？ -要什么？
I'm meeting someone called Natalie.
我想找个叫娜塔莉娅的人
Well, that's me.
我就是
Yeah. We met before, right?
我们见过面，是不是？
Then why am I here?
那么我来做什么？
I don't know. Tell me.
不知道，你自己说好了
I don't remember. I have no short-term memory. It's not amnesia.
我记不得，我没有短期记忆
Oh, you're the memory guy.
原来你是那个失忆的人
How do you know about me?
你怎么知道？
My boyfriend told me about you.
我男朋友提过你
Yeah? Who's your boyfriend?
你男朋友叫什么？
Jimmy Grants. Do you know him?
杰米・格兰斯，认识吗？
No.
不认识
Well, he knows you.
他认识你
He told me about you. He said you were staying at the Discount.
提到过你，说你住在特惠旅馆
In fact, a cop came by here earlier looking for you.
前不久有警察来找过你
Said he was looking for a guy who can't remember anything,
说要找一个…
wouldn't know how he got here or what he'd done.
懵懵懂懂的人
Said I get a lot of guys around here like that.
说我这里很多这种人
Well, you know, chronic alcoholism is one cause of short-term memory loss.
酗酒是短期失忆的一个原因
Are you Teddy?
你叫泰迪？
No. My name is Leonard.
不是，我叫莱纳
-Did Teddy send you? -I don't know.
-泰迪派你来？ -我不知道
What's happened to Jimmy?
杰米现在怎样了？
I don't know that either. Sorry.
我也不知道，对不起
You don't remember anything?
你什么都记不得？
You don't remember where you've been or what you've just done.
记不得去过哪里、做过什么？
No. I can't make new memories.
记不得，我没有短期记忆
Everything just fades.
什么都忘掉
Then why did you come here?
那么你来做什么？
I found this in my pocket.
我在口袋里找到这个
Your pocket.
你的口袋？
Bar bet. Care to contribute?
酒吧赌注，有兴趣参加吗？
No, thanks.
不用客气
It's for a lot of money.
彩金好多
Come on. Proceeds are going to charity. Help me out.
参加嘛，是慈善的
On the house.
免费
It's completely fucked because nobody believes you.
谁也不相信我
It's amazing what a little brain damage will do for your credibility.
脑部受损，连说话也没有人信
I guess it's some kind of poetic justice for not believing Sammy.
我以前不信萨米，应该有此报应
You know the truth about my condition, officer?
患我这种病的人…
You don't know anything.
什么都不知道
You feel angry, you don't know why.
生气生得莫名其妙
You feel guilty, you have no idea why.
内疚得莫名其妙
You could do anything and not have the faintest idea ten minutes later.
无论什么，十分钟就忘掉
Like Sammy. I could have done something like Sammy.
萨米的事…
I didn't tell you...
我有没有告诉你？
what happened to Sammy and his wife?
萨米和他太太的事
Well, she came to see me at my office.
她到我办公室见我
I thought she was just trying to catch me off guard,
我以为她在试探
so I didn't tell her what I really thought, but I never said that he was faking,
我没有对她说真心话
just that his condition was mental, not physical.
只说他的病是心理上的，而不是生理的
I found out later that she went home and gave Sammy his final exam.
她回家，替萨米做最后的测试
Sammy?
萨米
It's time for my shot.
到时间替我打针了
She knew beyond a doubt that he loved her.
她深信萨米爱她
So she found a way to test him.
于是用这个测试办法
Sammy.
萨米
It's time for my shot.
到时间替我打针了
She really thought she'd call his bluff.
她以为可以拆穿他
There you go.
打了
Or she just didn't wanna live with the things she put him through.
否则，她不想再活下去
Sammy.
萨米
It's time for my shot.
到时间替我打针了
It won't hurt.
不会痛
She went into a coma and never recovered.
她不省人事，接着就死了
Sammy couldn't understand or explain what happened.
萨米不明白，也不能解释
He's been in a home ever since.
从此长住疗养院
He doesn't even know that his wife's dead.
连妻子去世也不知道
I was wrong about Sammy, and I was wrong about his wife.
我看错了萨米，看错了他太太
She wasn't interested in the money. She just needed to understand his problem.
她不是为钱，只是想了解病情
His brain didn't respond to conditioning.
他对惯性没有反应
But he wasn't a con man.
可是他不是骗子
And when she looked into his eyes, she thought he could be the same person.
她以为萨米没有变
When I looked into his eyes, I thought I saw recognition.
我也以为萨米认得我
Now I know. You fake it.
我现在知道是假装的
If you're supposed to recognize somebody, you just pretend to.
他假装认得人
You bluff it to get a pat on the head from the doctors.
也许是为了博取赞许
You bluff it to seem less of a freak.
也许为了冒充正常
What drug dealer?
什么毒贩？
Hey, Lenny, how you doing?
莱尼，你好
It's private back here.
这是私人地方，出去！
It's okay. We know each other. Right, kid?
我们是认识的
How did you know I was here?
你怎么知道我在这里？
Oh, the Jag is out front. You should have put it around back.
你把美洲豹停在前面
What are you still doing here?
你还在这里做什么？
There's plenty of tattoo parlors up north.
北方有很多纹身店
I just wanted to get something down...
我想趁还没忘记
before it slipped my mind.
纹下来
Then give me the keys. I'll move it for you.
把车匙给我吧，我帮你开走
-It'll be all right for a minute. -Wait out there.
-不要紧 -出去等吧
Oh, for Christ...
唉
Look, give me a minute. I gotta get something for you.
等一等我好吗？
Fact six. Car license SG 137IU.
“事实6：车牌 SG1371U”
Look. Wait a minute, will ya?
等一等，好不好？
All right, we gotta get you out of here.
好，我要送你离开本地
-Why? -Aw, man.
为什么？
Come on, Leonard. How many times I gotta tell you?
多此一问，你要我说多少遍？
It's not safe for you to hang around here anymore.
你在这里已经不安全了
Why not?
为什么？
Because that cop's looking for you.
警察在找你
Now, I gotta get you a new identity, some new clothes. A different car would do for now. So put these on.
我要给你弄个新身份、新衣服 暂时换辆汽车，穿上去！
Whoa, whoa. What cop?
什么警察？
He's a bad cop. He's the one who checked you into the Discount Inn.
一个坏警察，他介绍你住特惠旅馆
He's been calling you for days,
他找了你已经好几天了
telling you shit, slipping envelopes under your door.
蒙骗你，把信封塞进你门底下
How do you know this?
你怎知道？
He told me. He thinks it's funny. He's been laughing at you.
他告诉我，以为好笑，他在玩你
You're full of shit.
你胡说
I'm not. He knows you're no good on the phone, so he's been calling you up.
不是，他知道你不爱讲电话…
Sometimes you don't answer the phone,
所以找上门
so he slips shit under your door to scare you into answering the phone again,
塞信封进你门里，吓到你听电话
giving you a line of crap about John G. Being some local drug dealer.
骗你说约翰・G是毒贩
Jimmy Grants.
杰米・格兰斯
Who's Jimmy Grants?
谁是杰米・格兰斯？
Leonard, Jimmy's the drug dealer.
杰米是毒贩
The cop wants to know how his operation's run.
警察在调查他
He's got some score in mind. Somehow you're involved.
无论如何，你牵涉进去了
How do you know him?
你怎么认识他的？
I'm a snitch. He's a cop from out of town.
我是线人，他是外地警察
The local boys put us together.
于是走在一起
If he knew I was helping you, he'd fucking kill me.
假如他知道我帮你，一定会宰了我
So take these clothes, put them on
换上这些衣服吧
and get the fuck out of here.
然后快点离开本地
Come on, Leonard. Just go.
莱纳，快走吧
You are full of shit.
你胡说
"Come by after. Natalie."
下班后来找娜塔莉娅
"Ferdy's Bar."
费迪斯酒吧
Hey, Jimmy.
杰米
I'm sorry. I, uh, thought you were somebody else. Sorry.
对不起，我…我认错了人
That's okay.
不要紧
So this Jimmy Grants deals drugs out of the bar where his girlfriend works?
杰米・格兰斯在女友的酒吧贩毒？
But he's not gonna bring her along. He'll come by himself, right?
他不会带她来，会自己来吧？
I always figured the drugs angle would be the best way to get him.
最好以贩毒罪名指控他
No, officer. I'm as ready as I'll ever be.
探长，我随时都准备好
You're in the lobby?
你来到了旅馆正门？
What do you look like?
你是什么样子？
I'll be right there.
我马上出去
Lenny.
莱尼
Officer Gammell.
你是盖玛探长？
Yeah. Come on.
对，来吧
Hey, smile.
笑一笑
Oh, don't... Not here.
不要…不要在这里
Over here.
这里拍吧
Now, is it Officer or Lieutenant Gammell?
是探长还是盖玛探员？
You know what? Don't write Gammell, just Teddy.
这样，不要写姓盖玛，写泰迪好了
Why?
为什么？
I'm undercover.
我正在做卧底
This is the directions where he's going.
他会经过
My number's on the bottom if you need me.
我的电话在下面
You're not coming?
你不来？
No. It wouldn't be appropriate.
不来，不方便去
Nice picture. I look thin.
拍得不错，拍得我瘦了些
Hey, Lenny.
莱尼
Make him beg.
好好修理他
Teddy!
泰迪
Jimmy.
杰米？
What the fuck are you doing here?
你在这里做什么？
You Jimmy Grants?
你是杰米・格兰斯？
Expecting any other Jimmys out here, Memory Man?
还有另一个杰米？白痴
Do you remember me?
你记得我？
Yeah, I remember you.
我记得你
Where the fuck's Teddy?
泰迪在哪里？
Well?
怎么样？
Motherfuck... What the fuck are you doing?
贱种…你想怎么样？
Strip.
脱掉
You're making a big fucking mistake, pal.
你搞错了，大错特错
Strip!
脱掉！
My associates are not the kind of people you wanna piss off.
我的拍档不是善男信女
Don't say anything else.
住口
-I knew I couldn't trust that fuck! -Take it off.
-早知到那贱种不可靠！ -脱掉
Your pants too.
裤子也脱掉
Why?
为什么？
I don't wanna get blood on them.
我不想沾血
Whoa, whoa, whoa. Wait, wait, wait. Did he tell you what I was bringing?
等一等，他有没有说我带了什么来？
Take your fuckin' pants off!
脱裤子呀
I've got two hundred grand stashed in the car!
我带了20万来！在车里！
Just take it!
拿走吧！
You think you can bargain with me?
你想讨价还价？
-Just take the money and walk away! -I don't want your money!
-把钱拿走吧！ -我不要你的臭钱！
Then what?
那么你要什么？
What do you want from me?
你要什么？
I want my fuckin' life back!
我要回我的生活！
Sammy.
“萨米”
He said "Sammy." How does he know about Sammy?
他说萨米，他认识萨米？
Oh, fuck.
糟糕
What have I done?
我做了什么？
Hey, mister, I need help.
先生，帮帮忙
There's a guy in here, he's hurt bad. We gotta get him to a doctor.
有人受了重伤，需要看医生
All right.
好
I don't know what happened. I've got this memory thing. Do I know you?
我是失忆的，我认识你吗？
No. Don't worry. I'm a cop.
不认识，我是警察
Is he still breathing?
他还有气吗？
I don't know. Maybe.
不知道，也许有
What the hell were you guys doing down here?
你们在这里干什么？
Well, I don't remember. I have this condition.
我不记得，我有病
Well, I hope it's not as serious as his, 'cause this guy's dead.
他比你惨，他死了
Ouch! Lenny!
哎唷，莱尼！
That shit kills! So you remember me now, huh?
痛死我了！你现在记得我了？
You are a fuckin' cop.
你是个警察
Yeah. And I'm the guy that helped you find him.
是我帮你找到他
Get up.
起来！
Lenny, you got the wrong idea.
莱尼，你误会了
Who is that? He knew me.
他是谁？他认识我
Of course he did. He raped your wife. He fucked up your brain.
当然，他强奸你老婆，打伤你
Bullshit. He's not the guy.
吹牛！他不是凶手
His name is James F. Grants. John G.
他叫杰米・格兰斯，又名约翰・G
Check your tattoos.
查查你的纹身吧
What was he bringing the two hundred grand for?
为什么他带20万来？
What?
什么？
What was it for?
用来干什么？
A load of amphetamines I told him I had.
我告诉他我有大批安非他命
-Is this a drug deal? -No. Yeah, that and your thing.
-你们买卖毒品？ -是，还有你的事
Look, Leonard, Jimmy's your guy.
杰米是你仇家
I just figured we'd make a few dollars on the side.
我只是乘机捞油水
-How did he know me? -The Discount Inn. He dealt out of there.
-他怎么认识我的？ -特惠旅馆
The guy at the front desk let him know if anybody came snooping around.
旅馆的人是他朋友
He called Jimmy the minute he saw you...
一看你拍照…
taking a picture of the dump.
就通知杰米
You're fucking using me.
你在利用我
No! You get half!
不，你分得一半的钱！
He knew about Sammy! Why would I tell him about fuckin' Sammy?
他认识萨米！怎么会认识萨米？
You tell everybody about Sammy, everybody who'll listen.
你见人就说萨米的事
"Remember Sammy Jankis?"
“记得杰克斯・萨米吗？”
Great story. It gets better every time you tell it.
你愈说愈精采
So you lie to yourself to be happy. There's nothing wrong with that. We all do it.
你在自己骗自已
Who cares if there's a few little details you'd rather not remember?
你只记得你想记得的事
-What the fuck are you talking about? -I don't know.
-你说什么？ -不知道
Your wife's surviving the assault.
你太太事后还活着
Her not believing your condition.
她不相信你有病
The torment and pain and anguish tearing her up inside.
她内心痛苦无比
The insulin.
胰岛素
That's Sammy, not me. I told you about Sammy.
那是萨米，不是我
Yeah, right. Like you tell yourself over and over again.
对，你不断这样对自己说
Conditioning yourself to remember.
用惯性法来帮自己记忆
Learning through repetition.
用重复又重复的方法来学习
Sammy let his wife kill herself. Sammy ended up in an institution.
萨米让太太自杀，萨米进了医院
Sammy was a con man, a faker.
萨米是老千，是假装的
I never said that Sammy was faking.
我从没说萨米假装
You exposed him for what he was...
你暴露出他的真面目
a fraud.
他的骗局
But I was wrong. That's the whole point.
不过，我是错的
See, Sammy's wife came to me.
萨米的妻子来找我
Sammy didn't have a wife.
萨米没有妻子
It was your wife who had diabetes.
你的妻子才有糖尿病
My wife wasn't diabetic.
我太太没有糖尿病
You sure?
你肯定？
Cut it out.
不要！
She wasn't diabetic.
她没有糖尿病
You think I don't know my own wife?
我难道不清楚我太太？
What the fuck is wrong with you?
你有什么不妥？
Well, I guess I can only make you remember the things you wanna be true.
你只记得你想记得的事
-Like old Jimmy down there. -He's not the right guy.
-就像杰米一样 -他不是我的仇人
He was to you.
对你来说，他是
Come on. You got your revenge. Enjoy it while you still remember.
你报了仇，趁记得，好好开心吧
What difference does it make whether he was your guy or not?
是不是真正的仇人，有什么关系？
It makes all the difference.
有很大的关系
-Why? You're never gonna know. -Yes, I will.
-你反正不会记得的 -我会的
-No, you won't. -I will.
-你不会 -我会的
-Somehow I'll know. -You won't remember!
-我总之会的 -你不会记得！
When it's done, I will know. It'll be different.
这次我会
Well, I thought so too. In fact, I was sure of it, but you didn't!
我本来以为你会，但你记不得
That's right.
对
The real John G. I helped you find him over a year ago.
真正的约翰・G，一年多前…
He's already dead.
我帮你找到他，他已经死了
Don't lie to me anymore.
不要再骗我
Look, Lenny.
莱尼
I was the cop assigned to your wife's case. I believed you.
你太太的档案是我给你的
I thought you deserved a chance for revenge.
我相信你，认为你应该报仇
I'm the one that helped you find the other guy in your bathroom that night,
我帮你找到另外的凶手
the guy that cracked your skull and fucked your wife.
那个打你的头，强奸你老婆的人
We found him. You killed him.
我们找到他，你杀了他
But you didn't remember.
可是你记不得
So I helped you...
于是我帮你…
start looking again,
再去找
looking for the guy you already killed.
找那个你已经杀掉的人
Oh, yeah. So who was he?
是吗？那么他是谁？
Just some guy. I mean, does it even matter who?
是谁有什么关系？
No reason, Lenny. No conspiracy. Just bad fucking luck.
两个吸毒的以为你太太独自在家
Couple of junkies too strung out to realize your wife didn't live alone.
倒霉起来，搞出大件事
But when you killed him, I was so convinced that you'd remember.
你杀了他，我还以为你记得
But it didn't stick.
不过，你忘掉了
Like nothing ever sticks. Like this won't stick.
什么都不记得，这次也不会记得
I took that picture...
照片是我拍的
just when you did it.
在你报仇的时候拍的
Look how happy you are.
看，你多开心
I wanted to see that face again.
我想你再开心点
Oh, gee, thanks.
多谢啊
Fuck you.
你这个混蛋
I gave you a reason to live, and you were more than happy to help.
你有仇报，生活就有目的
You don't want the truth...
你记不得真相，你自已…
You make up your own truth. Like your police file.
制造真相，例如那警察档案
It was complete when I gave it to you. Who took out the 12 pages?
谁撕掉里面的12页纸？
-You, probably. -No, it wasn't me. See, it was you.
-可能是你 -不是我，是你
Why would I do that?
我为什么撕掉？
To create a puzzle you could never solve.
为了替自己制造一个解不开的谜
Do you know how many... how many towns?
你知道有多少个镇吗？
How many John G's orJames G's? I mean, shit, Lenny, I'm a fucking John G.
有多少个约翰・G？我就是个约翰・G
-Your name is Teddy. -My mother calls me Teddy.
-你叫泰迪 -我妈妈叫我泰迪
My name's John Edward Gammell.
我的姓名是约翰・盖玛
Cheer up. There's plenty of John G's for us to find.
你要找，不愁没有约翰・G
All you do is moan.
你只知道发牢骚
I'm the one that has to live with what you've done.
只有我知道你做过什么
I'm the one that put it all together.
我在幕后指导
You, you wander around, you're playing detective.
你只是在扮侦探
You live in a dream, kid.
你活在梦中
A dead wife to pine for.
为亡妻怀念
A sense of purpose to your life.
有生活的目的
A romantic quest that you wouldn't end even if I wasn't in the picture.
即使没有我，你也不会罢手
I should kill you.
我应该杀你
Quit it. Lenny, come on.
收手吧，莱尼
You're not a killer.
你不是杀手
That's why you're so good at it.
所以你才那么在行
Come on. What are you doing? You know what time it is?
来，干什么？知道几点吗？
It's beer o'clock. I'm buying.
喝啤酒去吧，我请客
I'm not a killer.
我不是杀手
I'm just someone who wanted to make things right.
我只想补救错误
Can I just let myself forget what you've told me?
我应不应该忘记你的话？
Can I just let myself forget what you made me do?
应不应该忘记你让我做的事？
You think I just want another puzzle to solve?
你以为我想再去解另一个谜？
Another John G. To look for?
再去找另一个约翰・G？
You're a John G.
你也是约翰・G
So you can be my John G.
你可以做我的约翰・G
Do I lie to myself to be happy?
我要自欺才能够快乐？
In your case, Teddy,
泰迪，对于你…
yes, I will.
我会
Hey! Hey, that's not your car!
嗨，那辆车不是你的！
It is now.
现在是了
Jesus Christ, you can't take it!
你怎么可以开走？
Why not?
为什么不可以？
Because the guy you just killed owns it!
因为车主刚被你杀死
Somebody'll recognize it!
有人会认得
You know, I think I'd rather be mistaken for a dead guy than a killer.
被人误当成死人，比误当成杀手好
I might hang on to this for a while.
我会用一段时候
Lenny. Look, don't...
莱尼，不要…
Will you help me find the keys?
帮我找车钥匙好吗？
Lenny!
莱尼！
I have to believe in a world outside my own mind.
我要相信世界不是我想象出来的
I have to believe that my actions still have meaning,
我要相信我所做的事仍然有意义
even if I can't remember them.
即使我记不得做了什么
I have to believe that when my eyes are closed,
我要相信，即使闭上眼睛…
the world's still here.
世界仍然存在
Do I believe the world's still here?
我相不相信世界仍然存在？
Is it still out there?
世界仍然存在？
We all need mirrors to remind ourselves who we are.
我们需要记忆去确定自己的身份
I'm no different.
我并不例外
Now, where was I?
我到了哪里？